<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://www.climb.mx/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://www.climb.mx/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-09-21T05:08:06+00:00</updated><id>https://www.climb.mx/feed.xml</id><title type="html">climb.mx</title><subtitle>This my personal website, where I write, ponder my situation and the world around me, share pictures and other interesting things. My themes are related to Bitcoin, programming, bicycles, adventure, climbing.</subtitle><author><name>Everardo J. Barojas</name></author><entry><title type="html">Climb and bike: Uisang peak in Korea</title><link href="https://www.climb.mx/uisangbong/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Climb and bike: Uisang peak in Korea" /><published>2022-09-20T21:26:41+00:00</published><updated>2022-09-20T21:26:41+00:00</updated><id>https://www.climb.mx/Uisangbong</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.climb.mx/uisangbong/"><![CDATA[<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/wxOUIUkCiZA" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>]]></content><author><name>Everardo J. Barojas</name></author><category term="gear" /><category term="climbing" /><category term="travel" /><category term="Korea" /><category term="Corea" /><category term="Goran" /><category term="Kropp" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Quick video on this bike+hike day trip to Bukhansan mountains close to Seoul.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.climb.mx/assets/imgs/uisangbong/korea_bike.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.climb.mx/assets/imgs/uisangbong/korea_bike.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">On travelling</title><link href="https://www.climb.mx/on-travelling/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="On travelling" /><published>2022-07-25T23:26:41+00:00</published><updated>2022-07-25T23:26:41+00:00</updated><id>https://www.climb.mx/On-travelling</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.climb.mx/on-travelling/"><![CDATA[<!-- # On travelling -->

<p>As I’ve grown older, travelling has become more of a necessity for my mental health than an act of leisure. My destinations have become more and more particular but with less time to spare, so as always some interesting counterpoints.</p>

<p>With less time, I’ve found that mixing up activities can make the challenge more enjoyable, so I often look for the closest and largest mountain proceed to cycle to it and then climb it. This provides some interesting problem solving for the gear that I can take and makes the ride all the more epic.</p>

<p>In Korea, mountains are highly touristic places. Everybody loves a good mountain walk, and even politicians make it a point to be seen at the mountains. Top quality gear is abundant and crowds are a common sight. In fact, like many things in Korea it is a sharing experience.</p>

<p>One of the most peculiar things is that mountains in Korea are quite rocky and steep, often with beautiful granite slabs where friction climbing and exposure would be a significant challenge, however, all of the paths I experienced were completely intervened with chains, ropes, steel cables, steel stakes and even full flights of stairs in the steepest sections. A complete sacrilege of alpine and conservation standards and - some would argue - in detriment to the development of future athletes.</p>

<p>During my time there I climbed Uisang Peak, part of the Bukhan Mt. Where possible I tried to avoid the extra aid and climb by my own means, but in some places it was impossible due to the stairs or stakes being right where the only weaknesses of the route were (ie: cracks and gullies where you’d logically climb). This makes the mountains very accessible even to novice climbers, and if you want you can still do some sport or trad pitches where I assume the rock has been left intact.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/imgs/self.jpg" alt="Close to the summit of Uisangbong." />
<em>Close to the summit of Uisangbong.</em></p>

<p><img src="/assets/imgs/friend.jpg" alt="A Korean climber friend I made along the way." />
<em>A Korean climber friend I made along the way.</em></p>

<p>It’s quite impressive how different cultures develop the sport, I’d say there are about four development levels</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>Undeveloped. Trails are historical, no signals, map and compass required unless you know the area. Almost all Mexican trails are like this.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Trails and routes marked. Trails are or were maintained, there are signals for specific routes and trails, often found on tourist or specialty maps. This would be a run of the mill trail in the USA.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Trails and routes marked, maintained and new trails are being developed. Same as above, but trails are actively maintained and new trails are being developed without changing the difficulty of the original route. Typical trail systems in Europe.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Heavy infrastructure on trails like stairs, bridges, etc.  Typical trails in Korea and well, Everest.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>It’s completely clear that Korea is on the most developed level while Mexico is on the least.  The more developed an area, the easier it is for people to visit and the more the sport is developed. In my personal opinion, places like the Alps and the Pyrenees are the gold standard, great infrastructure like heated and well kept refuges, challenging routes for every level and minimal intervention to the rock or route. On the plus side, for people that enjoy adventure the least developed an area can be the most appealing and attractive.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/imgs/wall.jpg" alt="The sort of trails you find!" />
<em>The sort of trails you find.</em></p>

<p>As far as the cycling goes: driving culture is very very different from North America and Mexico in particular and we are definitely NOT used to the level of bike infrastructure that Seoul and the areas surrounding it have. Much like with trails, bike roads have dedicated super highways with their own bridges (like proper bridges that cross the 500m wide Han river), rest areas and in the main network around Seoul (hundreds of kms) it’s even illuminated!</p>

<!-- Nevertheless, some things hold true:

- Cars are not really careful

- Drivers act like they want to kill you

-  -->

<p><img src="/assets/imgs/Buddha.jpg" alt="This Buddha is the largest in East Asia, casually found in one the trails close to Uisanbong." />
<em>This Buddha is the largest in East Asia, casually found in one the trails close to Uisanbong.</em></p>]]></content><author><name>Everardo J. Barojas</name></author><category term="gear" /><category term="climbing" /><category term="travel" /><category term="Korea" /><category term="Corea" /><category term="touring" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[On how travelling has changed over the years, how I've mixed it with professional travel and some of my experiences in Korea.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.climb.mx/assets/imgs/wall.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.climb.mx/assets/imgs/wall.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">On reusing gear</title><link href="https://www.climb.mx/on-reusing-gear/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="On reusing gear" /><published>2022-07-24T07:26:41+00:00</published><updated>2022-07-24T07:26:41+00:00</updated><id>https://www.climb.mx/On-reusing-gear</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.climb.mx/on-reusing-gear/"><![CDATA[<!-- # Reusing old gear -->

<p>In the past months years I’ve grown into the hobby of woodworking and have come to appreciate hand-made things a bit more, which has led me away some of the more industrialised outdoor products out there.</p>

<p>One of those things is a pair of old Thom McCan boots that were involuntarily inherited from my father in law. I don’t think he ever used them as the soles looked like new. From what I gather they were bought in the 80s or 90s in Sears or similar. They are exquisitely hand-made in Italy. They are also goodyear welt, which means they are stitched and easy to resole. This traditional way of making shoes, still common in high quality work boots like Red Wing and the like is not light, and it is definitely not as easy to walk with as newer glued trekking boots that are closer in weight and construction methods to sneakers.</p>

<p>They held up quite well in a controlled environment, only caveat is the Vibram soles are a little bit old and the rubber seems to have hardened, stealing a little bit of grip in the process. I’m loving climbing with classic mountaineering boots though, they are solid and comfortable to boot!</p>

<p>Next time you find an old pair of hand-made shoes that someone wants to throw out, think if you can make them work for you.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/imgs/on_reusing_gear/boots.jpeg" alt="Goodyear welt boots with the classic red laces!" />
<em>Goodyear welt boots with the classic red laces!</em></p>]]></content><author><name>Everardo J. Barojas</name></author><category term="gear" /><category term="climbing" /><category term="travel" /><category term="Thom" /><category term="McCan" /><category term="goodyear" /><category term="welt" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Musings on reusing old gear.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.climb.mx/assets/imgs/on_reusing_gear/boots.jpeg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.climb.mx/assets/imgs/on_reusing_gear/boots.jpeg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Mountains meet Business (and how to move forward)</title><link href="https://www.climb.mx/mountains-meet-business/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Mountains meet Business (and how to move forward)" /><published>2022-07-22T01:26:41+00:00</published><updated>2022-07-22T01:26:41+00:00</updated><id>https://www.climb.mx/mountains-meet-business</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.climb.mx/mountains-meet-business/"><![CDATA[<!-- ## climb.mx: a deconstruction of nothing -->

<p>At a very different point in my life, I thought I would enhance my love of the mountains with my necessity to make money and I attempted to build a small mountain guiding operation. I wanted to appeal to foreigners and so I bought this domain: climb.mx.</p>

<p>There was not much intent in the structure of this attempt, however, in retrospect I see I had some of the basics right:</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>The URL, content and copy of climb.mx were good at targetting English speakers. In essence, climb.mx served as an inbound channel.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>At that point in my life, I considered myself an aspiring writer and as such, I was feeding the blog quite regularly and sharing actively, I was also travelling quite a bit and sharing with everyone on the road. So I did have a built in distribution strategy.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Not many fixed costs, as I was using a one click install server squatting on a server that was already being paid for by a friend. I easily broke even with my first guided ascent. Another close friend was managing the largest mountain related CMS in LaTam and we bartered some clients that he referred for a couple of crampons and ice axes I could continue to use for my clients, and since I was already climbing quite actively I didn’t need to purchase any gear for myself.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>The variable costs were essentially expenses and mostly transferred to the customer. As for pricing, at some point I was told by some experienced guides that I should charge at least 100USD / day, and never less to protect those who were living off this, so that’s what I did.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>I bundled some packages (Izta from DF, Ajusco, Pico and of course Custom trip) which made it easy for foreigners to <em>convert</em> to a sale.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>The big and tangible problem was with the goods that I was selling. I was selling my time, hence I was in the consulting business. In retrospect though, I can really say that mountain guiding is the most work intensive consultancy I have personally experienced. Not only do you need knowledge, experience and very good equipment, but you need to constantly train in order to be significantly stronger than your clients. On top of that, the services that you are rendering are performed under very unfavourable conditions: at altitude, in inhospitable places with unpredictable weather and with the constant knowledge that if you mess up someone might die.</p>

<p>I quickly found out that although 100USD / day seemed like a decent tariff for a 25yr old aspiring mountaineer, it didn’t really compensate for the stress that each of these ascents was generating. If consultancy makes money with your time, guided ascents make money with your risk, sweat and life.</p>

<p>I quit guiding after roughly 2014 - at that point I was subrogating the actual ascent to local guides and taking care of logistics- but I kept this domain and used it is a creative outlet of sorts.</p>

<p>Some months ago I decided Wordpress was slow + boring and switched to using Jekyll as a labour of love and learning. I hadn’t worked on a Ruby based framework for a while and was using (and enjoying) Docusaurus for a professional project, my decision had the intrinsic objective of getting me to write better and more with less distractions and such, (we’ll see about that).</p>

<p>I made the switch and here it is, a newer, more basic, less is more version of the climb.mx that you (whoever you are) know and love.</p>

<p>Everardo</p>]]></content><author><name>Everardo J. Barojas</name></author><category term="long" /><category term="distance" /><category term="cycling" /><category term="bicycle" /><category term="climbing" /><category term="travel" /><category term="xbike" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.climb.mx/assets/imgs/10247068594_d47b8a25c7_b.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.climb.mx/assets/imgs/10247068594_d47b8a25c7_b.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Manual del Ciclista Valeverguista</title><link href="https://www.climb.mx/manual-del-ciclista-valeverguista/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Manual del Ciclista Valeverguista" /><published>2018-10-31T22:49:32+00:00</published><updated>2018-10-31T22:49:32+00:00</updated><id>https://www.climb.mx/manual-del-ciclista-valeverguista</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.climb.mx/manual-del-ciclista-valeverguista/"><![CDATA[<h4 id="el-valeverguismo-integral">El Valeverguismo Integral</h4>

<p>Hace muchos años, un par de amigos me platicaron sobre su filosofía de la vida, prima hermana del Budismo tibetano y ligeramente semejante al Zen: El <em>valeverguismo integral, que</em> principalmente consiste en no preocuparse demasiado y dejar que las cosas pasen: Heráclito lo resume mucho mejor que ellos con su principio de, Panta Rhei (lit. <em>todo fluye</em>). Es decir, deja que fluya la vida.</p>

<p>Hoy quiero platicar cómo he aprendido a aplicar esto sobre la bicicleta como medio de transporte, y de cómo he hecho para sobrevivir 20 años de rodar en esta y otras ciudades.</p>

<h4 id="el-ciclista-dentro-de-todos">El Ciclista Dentro de Todos</h4>

<p>A lo largo de mi vida he pedaleado por varias partes del mundo primer y tercermundista. He recorrido las calles amistosas de Suiza, el país de los topes (México), las imposibles subidas de los Alpes, el camino más alto de América y hasta los Fiordos de Noruega.</p>

<p>Quisiéramos creer que México es un lugar horrible para pedalear, pero la verdad es que no tanto. Hay riesgo de que un auto te mate en todos los sitios donde convivas con autos y en donde no, muy probablemente te puedes lastimar de muchos otros modos interesantes.</p>

<p><strong>La bicicleta es un deporte riesgoso.</strong></p>

<p>En todos estos años, mi única enseñanza es que la prioridad es <em>sobrevivir,</em> siempre<em>.</em> Hoy, mientras iba por una ciclovía atascada de obstáculos: niños jugando, cargadores descargando, gente sentada y coches tratando de entrar y salir de gasolineras, tuve una revelación:</p>

<h4 id="el-manifiesto-del-ciclista-superviviente">El Manifiesto del Ciclista Superviviente</h4>

<p>Hay tres prioridades cuando uno va sobre una bicicleta:</p>

<ol>
  <li>Sobrevivir,</li>
  <li>No lastimar a nadie,</li>
  <li>Llegar del punto A al punto B.</li>
</ol>

<p>Todas las decisiones que uno toma deben considerar estas prioridades. Por ejemplo, estás a punto de salirte de la ciclovía para esquivar una patrulla estacionada, puedes escoger a) salir hacia la autovía o b) subir a la banqueta. Lo que debes pensar es ¿en qué vía tengo mayor posibilidades de lastimarme?, ¿puedo lastimar a alguien en el proceso? y por último ¿este camino me sigue llevando al punto B?</p>

<p>La respuesta correcta es b) – si te incorporas a la autovía y la patrulla abre la puerta, o hace un movimiento raro, o te enrielas en el concreto o te caes, estarás objetivamente expuesto al tráfico vehicular.</p>

<h4 id="el-ciclista-sobreviviente-siempre-es-valeverguista">El Ciclista Sobreviviente Siempre es Valeverguista</h4>

<p>La infraestructura ni en Suiza, ni en Amsterdam, ni en Oregon, ni en México es perfecta. El ciclista sobreviviente siempre es valeverguista porque si siguiéramos los protocolos de tránsito estaríamos muertos.</p>

<p>Por ejemplo — algunas vías de metrobus están señalizadas para llevar ciclistas, algunos carriles de contraflujo también. Pero, ¿dónde tengo mayores oportunidades de sobrevivir ante un accidente? Estimado léctor, no sé si lo sepa, pero los conductores de metrobus tienen instrucciones claras de priorizar la vida de sus pasajeros sobre la de 1 (un) transeúnte, lo cual es lógico y valido. Eso significa que ellos están entrenados para escoger atropellarte antes de tratar de esquivarte y arriesgarse a lastimar a las múltiples personas que llevan arriba. Ustedes decidan, pero yo no comparto carril con un vehículo que está entrenado para atropellarme.</p>

<p>Si pedaleas en la ciudad, algún día vas a tener un accidente, lo siento mucho, no es cuestión de si va a pasar, sino de cuándo y cómo. No tienes capacidad de elegir ni de controlar cómo ni cuándo, pero <em>sí</em> tienes capacidad de controlar en qué vías te mueves y resulta que es más probable que sobrevivas a un choque contra un auto, que contra un camión de carga. Por eso, debes evitar vías por donde pasan camiones de carga. Escoge vías pequeñas, por donde circulen autos, motos y bicis. No escojas un eje vial con un carril en contraflujo en donde si pierdes el equilibrio vayas a dar abajo de las llantas de un trailer o un trolebus.</p>

<p>Para cerrar con broche de oro les dejo esta cita de Henry David Thoreau, de su ensayo Civil Desobedience.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Must the citizen ever for a moment, or in the least degree, resign his conscience to the legislator? Why has every man a conscience then? I think that we should be men first, and subjects afterward. It is not desirable to cultivate a respect for the law, so much as for the right. The only obligation which I have a right to assume is to do at any time what I think right.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Que se traduce así: ¿Acaso el ciudadano, aunque sea por un instante, debe renunciar a su conciencia y adoptar la del legislador? ¿Cuál sería el propósito de nuestra conciencia entonces? Creo que deben ir los individuos primero y los sujetos después. No es deseable cultivar respeto por la ley, sino por nuestro derecho. <strong>La única obligación que tengo derecho de asumir, es que en todo momento haga lo que me parece correcto.</strong></p>

<p>Así con la bici, y así con la vida. Al ciclista superviviente le deben de valer verga (disculpen la palabra, es creencia religiosa) las reglas. Su única regla es la supervivencia.</p>

<p><strong><em>Superesse semper,</em></strong></p>

<p>Everardo J Barojas</p>]]></content><author><name>admin</name></author><category term="Biking Shenanigans" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[El Valeverguismo Integral]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.climb.mx/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_5167-821x510.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.climb.mx/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_5167-821x510.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">An Alternative Ending</title><link href="https://www.climb.mx/an-alternative-ending/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="An Alternative Ending" /><published>2018-07-15T17:51:20+00:00</published><updated>2018-07-15T17:51:20+00:00</updated><id>https://www.climb.mx/an-alternative-ending</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.climb.mx/an-alternative-ending/"><![CDATA[<p>After sleeping under the stars for 978 days and travelling the entire length of the equator several times, he packed his bike into a neat little box and boarded a flight back to his home country. He was a borne adventurer, a rough man with a steady, firm, handshake and worn out hands that would regularly get him out of trouble in his travels. He arrived at the airport with time to spare, checked in his bike in a box and boarded the plane.</p>

<p>The state of the art 878 airplane had an impecable flight record, yet that day it had two simultaneous engine failures and crashed in a remote part of Africa.</p>

<p>There were reportedly no survivors. The remains of the fuselage were found 8 years after the crash by a non profit organization funded and led by his sister (a well known author and nobel laureate). The remains were apparently intact, except for heavy damage from the sun, wind, wild animals and a small hole made in the cargo compartment.</p>

<p>Thorough inventory checks showed that the bicycle was missing and his remains could never be positively identified. Years later, Dr. Passo, a genetic archaelogist that studied the relation between African genes and local artforms, found a particular tribe in the most inmaccessible parts of the Jira mountains with a genetic strand related to that of our adventurer. Upon this notice, his nobel sister quiclkly assembled a team and set off in a sea worthy vessel acquired by the non profit org. They arrived to Africa shortly thereafter.</p>

<p>A series of extensive laboratory tests, confirmed that the tribe in question had developed an outstanding mastery of hand labour and were astonished to learn that the tribe in question had adopted the handshake as a means of formal and informal salutation within the past 50 years.</p>

<p>After years of sociological studies by an artifficial intelligence instance completely modelled on the works of Dr Levi Strauss, the handshake in question was traced back to a government adviser who had travelled extensively and met several european personalities. The adviser had a very solitary life and recently passed, he had been buried, according to tradition, with his most valued possesions, next to the remains of of his pet, a domestic mountain lion. Several large scale attempts were made to lacate his next of kin, but alas, they were all unsuccessful.</p>

<p>In keeping with religous observances, The remains in question were never exhumed, and although there were rumors of a two wheeled steel artifact, the team focused on trying to correlate the newly developed tribe dynamics to the genetic information of the adventurer. In a last resort effort, the non profit company tried to trace the genetic strands of the mysterious adviser to its ancestors, they were stunned to find that he beared no relation with any tribe around.</p>

<p>Years of analysis on the tribe members yielded the base data for a russian laboratory to program an advanced simulation to be executed through a 10 year timeframe on state wide distributed super computer, fractionally powered by the russian nuclear reserve. The ambitious project simulated the entire universe, through time and space until the point of the plane crash and was designed to calculate the possibilities of surviving such a crash. The results proved that such a crash would effectively erase any memories, and that if a human were to survive, it would be highly likely that the personality of such victim be unrecognisable.</p>

<p>After a lifetime of research, the nobel sister had a breakthrough discovery, brought through by the laboratory in Russia. After more that 30 years running paralel simualtions of millions of possible universes with slight variations, enough information was acquired to ascertain that a 70 kilogram male could survive that very plane crash, and under very specific conditions, learn an african dialect and be accepted as. Functioning member of society. The nobel sister had accrued significant wealth throigh these discoveries and died less than a month later in a laboratory accident while trying to extract genetic information from a live predator.</p>

<p>There were no succesors of the family, yet the non profit organization became the largest privately owned caregiver in Africa and was awarded a permanent patent on any sort of simulation of the universe. The African tribe gained worldwide notoriety for their exceptional endurance, winning a streak of more than a hundred ultramarathons all over the world, most of them on a bicycle. The world leaders that had met them, were particularly taken with their firm, steady and confident handshake.</p>]]></content><author><name>Everardo J. Barojas</name></author><category term="long" /><category term="distance" /><category term="cycling" /><category term="audax" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[After sleeping under the stars for 978 days and travelling the entire length of the equator several times, he packed his bike into a neat little box and boarded a flight back to his home country. He was a borne adventurer, a rough man with a steady, firm, handshake and worn out hands that would regularly get him out of trouble in his travels. He arrived at the airport with time to spare, checked in his bike in a box and boarded the plane.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.climb.mx/assets/imgs/10247068594_d47b8a25c7_b.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.climb.mx/assets/imgs/10247068594_d47b8a25c7_b.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Holger Franz Hagenbusch: A Professional Opinion</title><link href="https://www.climb.mx/murders-in-mexico/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Holger Franz Hagenbusch: A Professional Opinion" /><published>2018-05-06T05:28:12+00:00</published><updated>2018-05-06T05:28:12+00:00</updated><id>https://www.climb.mx/murders-in-mexico</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.climb.mx/murders-in-mexico/"><![CDATA[<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">I feel a pretty deep connection to Holger Franz Hagenbusch. I met him on a beatiful morning on the mountain pass between Iztaccíhuatl and Popocatépetl. I</span> recognized him instantly as a fellow bike traveller, upon deeper examination we found that we had both lived close to the town Bochum, in Germany. I had looked exactly like he looked in december 2010 when I had climbed that very road to Paso de Cortés with my bike, on my way to Chiapas and eventually Cancún, just like him.</p>

<p>Skipping most of the usual questions I jumped right into the direction and duration of his trip, of course, asking about his equipment. We talked about his bike, a Surly. A german with a Surly? Pretty remarkable and unusual combination. And without a Rohloff? Even weirder. Holger explained that he had built this bike in America – I inspected his bike closely. It was a Long Haul Trucker with a front and rear panniers. I used to travel with a Surly Cross Check and loved it. I travelled the baja, chihuahua, mexico cancun, Barcelona to Slovenia, the pyrenees and Norway with it. All before it was taken from me in the city of Guadalajara. A group of 5 people took it from me. Apparently they only wanted my cell phone –These amateur mexican robbers had no idea what my bike was worth. To add insult to injury, there was no signal to unlock my phone from the icloud account that protected it and they grew ever more anxious. They dragged me away from the street and into some train tracks, I could hear the train coming at a distance. They made me kneel and pushed a gun right to the back of my head. GIVE ME THE PASSWORD! They demanded. ‘I’m telling you the password’, I replied, ‘but it’s not working’, I explained there was no signal, really not wanting to die giving customer support to a group of disgruntled idiots.</p>

<p>They beat me up a little every time the password did’t work. The train horn broke the silence intermittently as it was nearing. They were losing their patience. They threatened to hit me with the butt of the gun and leave my body on the train tracks for the train to dispose of. Their shouting grew louder, their beating me up too, the cold steel pressed to my head every time they asked for the password. The sound of the train now an impossible roar– WAIT, I said: take my bike!! It’s worth more than the phone! ‘How much?’ they asked–I hesitated, not wanting to disclose the full price… about 10,000! OK, they said. They disappeared to the other side of the tracks, just before the train passed and left me there kneeling. I could see my white, custom Surly Cross Check rolling through the train gaps beneath the passing cars. It was a lucky getaway for me. I’m lucky to be alive.</p>

<p>Today, I can’t help but remember when in 2010 I rode the exact same road that Holger died on. <a href="http://montanismo.org/2011/viajar_en_bicicleta_o_como_ver_un_pais_desde_dentro/2/">Back then I wrote:</a></p>

<blockquote>
  <p>My opinions on the zapatista movement are generally neutral. I must say I feel empathy and completely disagree with the military and political oppression in the area, however I am not an expert on the subject, and it’s not my intention to judge, but this is what I lived through when I went by:</p>

  <p>“They will rob you here, you know? They say they are zapatistas and even if they’re not, they will fuck you”. That is the first thing I heard when I entered Ocosingo, from a group of teenagers. –the next thing I heard was “If I were you, I’d just go back, it’s going to get dark and all hell will break loose”.</p>
</blockquote>

<figure aria-describedby="caption-attachment-654" class="wp-caption aligncenter" id="attachment_654" style="width: 592px">[![3229-ever08_g](http://climb.mx/wp-content/uploads/2018/05/3229-ever08_g-300x186.jpg)](http://climb.mx/wp-content/uploads/2018/05/3229-ever08_g.jpg)<figcaption class="wp-caption-text" id="caption-attachment-654">Sign in Ocosingo highway that reads: “You are entering Zapatista territory, rebellious, here the people rule, the government obeys”.</figcaption></figure>
<p>It is notable that this incident happened almost in the exact same place where Holger was found, in the same road. I shiver when I think of this. I’ve ridden my share of roads, races and courses. Holger Franz Hagenbusch and Krzystof Chmielwski were not <a href="http://www.eluniversal.com.mx/estados/localizan-en-una-barranca-restos-del-ciclista-aleman">part of an accident as the authorities have said</a>. Their bodies did not end up in that cliff after being hit by any car. They were purposely thrown there after being murdered, <strong>I have no doubts about it.</strong></p>

<ol>
  <li>I’ve ridden that road, it is not dangerous, car wise.</li>
  <li>Bikers uphill tend to distance themselves, especially when their gear differs as greatly as these guys’ did, (bike trailer vs. no bike trailer).</li>
  <li><strong>You do not lose control of a bike while going uphill.</strong></li>
  <li>The whole idea that the this is an accident is completely ridiculous.</li>
</ol>

<p>Having travelled through most of my country, I can only say that the dangers are becoming un manageable. I have been robbed several times, <a href="http://montanismo.org/2006/cerro_telapon_y_rio_frio_altamente_peligrosos/">Humberto Cabrera was shot in the face by a .45 caliber illegal weapon</a>, I barely survived the ordeal in Guadalajara I described before, and Holger will never ride his bike because of this. <strong>The people responsible for this should be prosecuted to the full extent of the law.</strong></p>

<p>* Cover picture is a self portrait taken on the road from Tuxtla Gutierrez to San Cristobal de las Casas in 2010; Holger’s instagram: https://www.instagram.com/kozmopolit_by_bike/ ; Holger’s website: http://www.kozmopolit.de/en/</p>]]></content><author><name>admin</name></author><category term="Biking Shenanigans" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I feel a pretty deep connection to Holger Franz Hagenbusch. I met him on a beatiful morning on the mountain pass between Iztaccíhuatl and Popocatépetl. I recognized him instantly as a fellow bike traveller, upon deeper examination we found that we had both lived close to the town Bochum, in Germany. I had looked exactly like he looked in december 2010 when I had climbed that very road to Paso de Cortés with my bike, on my way to Chiapas and eventually Cancún, just like him.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.climb.mx/wp-content/uploads/2018/05/3229-ever04_g.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.climb.mx/wp-content/uploads/2018/05/3229-ever04_g.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Your stupid lifestyle</title><link href="https://www.climb.mx/your-stupid-lifestyle/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Your stupid lifestyle" /><published>2016-02-19T18:30:00+00:00</published><updated>2016-02-19T18:30:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.climb.mx/your-stupid-lifestyle</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.climb.mx/your-stupid-lifestyle/"><![CDATA[<p>We have always needed to work to get what we want, that isn’t new. From time long past, the work we required to do involved a certain amount of physical activity, we traded abilities for goods, goods for other goods or daughters for land, all of them required hard work. Even after currency was implemented as a medium of exchange, after Plato’s Akademia came into being (the birth of the geek who sat on chairs and thought for a living), after the industrial revolution and after the invention of many other commodities, we still had to perform physical exertion, if not for anything else, to physically transport ourselves.</p>

<p>Our bodies are meant to perform physical exertion, even at a chemical and physical level, and psychologically as well there is no denying that what we now call exercise, which used to be part of what we called life, is not only healthy, but even necessary. Yet, we drive on huge moving cars, trains or buses, we ride on elevators, escalators, even doors are automatic nowadays… and it turns out that all this is not healthy for us, it’s damaging our well being and costing us thousands on medical bills, health magazines, sports equipment and yes, on gyms. What is a gym? For most of us, a gym is where you go compensate for your everyday lack of activity -unless you’re a top athlete, or under physical rehab in which case there is no substitute-.</p>

<p>It’s a wonderful irony: We avoid manual means of locomotion at all costs, we ride on toll freeways or high speed trains to “save” time yet, come the afternoon we flock to the gym, running on treadmills staring at “sports” on a TV or taking a detailed look at the seams of the shorts on our partners arse while riding on a static bike. We drive on a car to get to a gym, where we ride on a bike that doesn’t move. Wouldn’t it be better to just ride a bike to the gym? In fact, wouldn’t it be better to skip the gym altogether and ride to work/school? – But I live way too far to ride to work, plus it’s dangerous, plus it’ll ruin my hair, the more sofisticated reader might ponder. But he could still do part of it on a bike, mixing it with whichever public transport he wishes or with small walks or he could avoid elevators, take the stairs and all the while work on his Gluteus Maximus. Life is full of possibilities indeed, and I maintain that the greatest, cheapest and most accessible exercise apparatus is the omnipresent floor, the common stairs a solid second.</p>

<p>However, there is a bigger problem, because if you take a closer look, it turns out a lot of these activities (cars and transport) are harmful for the environment as well… and now I must note, hoping I’m not coming across as a total luddite, hippie or both: I love technology -I’m a mechatronic engineer- big on programming and high tech stuff. The problem is I was recently introduced to the concept of a Progress Trap and frankly it seems we’ve fallen on a few of such traps, I’m rather sure of it:</p>

<p><em>A progress trap is the condition human societies experience when, in pursuing progress through human ingenuity, they inadvertently introduce problems they do not have the resources or political will to solve.</em></p>

<p>I’m worried, after familiarizing myself with the subject, a fear for our own contriving collective intelligence and diminishing future has begun to grow on me. The clearest and most typical example of a progress trap is the invention of the beloved automobile. It’s no wonder to me that even Aldos Huxley’s god in his dystopian classic A Brave New World is named after Henry Ford. The automobile has been a status of progress and indeed an advantageous addition to our lives, it truly has changed the world. However, in the big scheme of things, it has contributed as much to our wellbeing as a cheesecake to a weight watchers meeting.</p>

<p>Don’t get me wrong, I like cars, I own two of them, they are great examples of human ingenuity and most of the times, they make our lives better, but nowadays, in a society that strives to eradicate atomic power, reduce CO2 emission to zero, become self sustainable and healthier, cars as we know them, well, they don’t really fit in, do they? But that’s the part of the progress trap concept that’s really scary, we designed all this amazing boats, trains and cars to transport all kinds of things half way around the world at a reasonable cost. We created a society sustained by a global economy dependent on all these transported goods -this is relatively new- and as it happens, it is precisely these things that are causing global warming, over cropping, pollution and non-sustainable commerce, yet we are too far along to turn around, to hooked on the stuff to stop, we can’t go back.</p>

<p>We can’t take cows back to Europe, we can’t take oranges away from New Yorkers -as little as 50 years ago it was not uncommon for New Yorkers to receive oranges from California as a Christmas present- or apples (electronic or otherwise) out of international markets. We are proverbially “fucked”, the plane has crashed into the mountain and we continue to collectively pull on the throttle, ignoring all of the solutions that we already have, mostly because they are not to our -and I mean our society’s- short-term economical advantage. Emphasis on solutions we already have, because we do, consider the following:</p>

<figure aria-describedby="caption-attachment-635" class="wp-caption aligncenter" id="attachment_635" style="width: 422px">[![bakfiets](http://climb.mx/wp-content/uploads/2016/02/bakfiets-300x200.jpg)](http://climb.mx/wp-content/uploads/2016/02/bakfiets.jpg)<figcaption class="wp-caption-text" id="caption-attachment-635">Bicycles are not only for sporting, they are also a good way to move from A to B, substitute kids for a few cases of beer to appeal to a younger audience.</figcaption></figure>
<p>I must confess I can think of many reasons for not using bicycles in Mexico City, one of them very important: it’s suicide, in a city with 28 million? It has to be. Everyday bicycle commuting in a city as big and chaotic as this one must be scary at best, or plain life threatening, depending. The utopian image shown in the picture above is probably not found in the bulk of this city, right? Perhaps on cherry picked areas and situations, which brings me to my next, seemingly contradictory point: You can cherry pick your situation and safely ride your bike to your job or school, and for that I will provide you, my avid reader, with a list:</p>

<ol>
  <li>Use common sense, which is surprisingly uncommon</li>
  <li>Polish your bike skills, ride with your eyes open and no headphones, attention is paramount. Your life depends on it</li>
  <li>Invest some time into finding a viable (read: safe) route</li>
  <li>Get some lights that are really visible</li>
  <li>Ride defensively and always expect the worst; parked cars will open their doors, crossing cars <em>haven’t</em> seen you, pedestrians will jaywalk, assume massive potholes are everywhere, motorbikes will try to shove you off the road and trucks/peseros/camiones will go out of their way to block your safe passage and murder you</li>
  <li>Admit that cars are killing machines and avoid them like the plague; better to do a few extra kilometres on an empty street, than to save 20 minutes. Exercise, good. Risk, bad</li>
  <li>Use a bicycle lock that is at least 10% of the cost of your bicycle, otherwise you might get there, but your bike won’t last long</li>
</ol>

<p>Find a nice, safe, enjoyable route. Do whatever it takes. Use Google street view, drive around, ride your bicycle, scooter or skateboard and find streets without cars, try small pedestrian streets, side streets which you would normally avoid. You can ride on the sidewalk (carefully). In this city, bicycles are not respected by cars, trucks or anyone. Public transport <em>will</em> try to run you over and there is almost no specific infrastructure -apart from a few upper class neighbourhoods, there are few usable bike lanes- but this can all be turned to your advantage. The city is yours; cyclists are above the law, or maybe just under it but it doesn’t matter. If you strive to reduce your carbon footprint, be healthier, thinner, look better and save money on transport, gasoline and gyms, you can do it. Think about this next time you complain about traffic, polluting trucks or the ridiculously unintelligent doble no circula policy.</p>

<figure aria-describedby="caption-attachment-634" class="wp-caption aligncenter" id="attachment_634" style="width: 402px">[![Bike_Taxi](http://climb.mx/wp-content/uploads/2016/02/Bike_Taxi-300x201.jpg)](http://climb.mx/wp-content/uploads/2016/02/Bike_Taxi.jpg)<figcaption class="wp-caption-text" id="caption-attachment-634">If he can do it, so can you. Photograph by Luis Arcadio de Jesús.</figcaption></figure>
<p>Everardo J. Barojas</p>]]></content><author><name>admin</name></author><category term="Biking Shenanigans" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[We have always needed to work to get what we want, that isn’t new. From time long past, the work we required to do involved a certain amount of physical activity, we traded abilities for goods, goods for other goods or daughters for land, all of them required hard work. Even after currency was implemented as a medium of exchange, after Plato’s Akademia came into being (the birth of the geek who sat on chairs and thought for a living), after the industrial revolution and after the invention of many other commodities, we still had to perform physical exertion, if not for anything else, to physically transport ourselves.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.climb.mx/assets/imgs/10247068594_d47b8a25c7_b.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.climb.mx/assets/imgs/10247068594_d47b8a25c7_b.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Norway 2014</title><link href="https://www.climb.mx/norway-2014/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Norway 2014" /><published>2015-02-10T07:35:21+00:00</published><updated>2015-02-10T07:35:21+00:00</updated><id>https://www.climb.mx/norway-2014</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.climb.mx/norway-2014/"><![CDATA[<iframe allowfullscreen="" frameborder="0" height="371" mozallowfullscreen="" src="//player.vimeo.com/video/118741813" title="The Golden Sun" webkitallowfullscreen="" width="660"></iframe>

<p>Click here to watch the full article with pictures, map and descriptions :-)</p>

<h2 id="httpphotoclimbmx"><a href="http://photo.climb.mx">http://photo.climb.mx</a></h2>]]></content><author><name>admin</name></author><category term="Uncategorized" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.climb.mx/assets/imgs/10247068594_d47b8a25c7_b.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.climb.mx/assets/imgs/10247068594_d47b8a25c7_b.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The Trip pt. 1</title><link href="https://www.climb.mx/the-trip-pt-1/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Trip pt. 1" /><published>2012-03-10T03:24:07+00:00</published><updated>2012-03-10T03:24:07+00:00</updated><id>https://www.climb.mx/the-trip-pt-1</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.climb.mx/the-trip-pt-1/"><![CDATA[<p>After a few days of “bullshitting” (ie: blogging) my way through life and lying to myself about the <em>epicness</em> of my future trip, I managed to actually leave my home with my new non-custom made non-hand built bike; an <a href="http://www.retrobike.co.uk/gallery2/d/60222-2/Ascent+EX.jpg">’89 DiamondBack Ascent EX</a> bought for exactly 8 bags of peanuts. Indeed, my <em>vintage</em> rig <a href="http://nextround.net/wp-content/uploads/2009/04/bling_bike.jpg">was bling</a>, and updated with modern components I was quite happy to explore mexico’s darkest off roads.</p>

<figure class="wp-caption alignnone" style="width: 444px">![Of bikes &amp; men](http://mxclimb.files.wordpress.com/2012/03/bike.jpg "Of bikes &amp; men")<figcaption class="wp-caption-text">My tasteful vintage touring rig.</figcaption></figure>
<p>This time, the leaving part was not done alone (there´s a first time for everything), instead I left with a dear friend of mine: <a href="http://youtu.be/n3GdCnugMiY">Mario, with whom I have climbed</a> for many years. He was to ride with me for the first five days, after which I would continue alone. Cycling with a friend is not as nice as you might think though (lots of waiting/decision making involved). However, <em>travelling</em> with a friend <em>is</em> much better than going at it alone, especially when you camp, sightsee or just hang out. Truth be told, the biking part is possibly worst, because unless you ride at exactly the same pace, either you’re waiting for someone or stressed of having to catch up with him; it’s the other things that really take a turn for the better. At the risk of sounding like a new age, pacifist hippie (which of course, I am) these things become really important when you’re alone for a long time.</p>

<p>If <a href="http://climb.mx/2012/02/08/riding-the-highest-road-in-north-america/" title="Riding the highest road in North America">you’ve read this other post</a>, you can probably infer that the main purpose of the trip was to climb. And honoring this purpose, the climbing started almost right away; you pretty much <em>have</em> to climb to get out of Mexico city because it’s a valley. The first climb leads to Milpa Alta and eventually down to Amecameca, the last important town before entering the national park that hosts Iztaccíhuatl and Popocatépetl. It is a beautiful climb that many riders use to leave Mexico city and the ensuing descent is equally entertenaing, as it meanders through some very ancient country where maize has been grown for thousands of years.</p>

<figure class="wp-caption alignnone" style="width: 579px">![Milpa Alta](http://mxclimb.files.wordpress.com/2012/03/straw.jpg "Milpa Alta")<figcaption class="wp-caption-text">Looking down from the third "mirador", the summit of the Milpa Alta col.</figcaption></figure>
<figure class="wp-caption alignnone" style="width: 579px">![Getting close to Amecameca](http://mxclimb.files.wordpress.com/2012/03/blur.jpg "Getting close to Amecameca")<figcaption class="wp-caption-text">Beautiful agricultural landscapes give way to mountains.</figcaption></figure>
<p>Having now really left the massive amorphous urban blob that we call D.F, the true adventure started as we snailed slowly through the landscape that I would come to childishly call home for the next month: the trans volcanic belt.</p>

<figure class="wp-caption alignnone" style="width: 436px">![The Popo](http://mxclimb.files.wordpress.com/2012/03/thepope.jpg "The Popo")<figcaption class="wp-caption-text">A partial eclipse of the heart.</figcaption></figure>
<p>Home sweet home: leaving that view behind, we knew we were headed for a nice trip and that maybe we were not underestimating the <em>epicness</em> of mexican off-roads, it’s amazing how re-assuring a nice view can be.</p>]]></content><author><name>cheve5</name></author><category term="Biking Shenanigans" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[After a few days of “bullshitting” (ie: blogging) my way through life and lying to myself about the epicness of my future trip, I managed to actually leave my home with my new non-custom made non-hand built bike; an ’89 DiamondBack Ascent EX bought for exactly 8 bags of peanuts. Indeed, my vintage rig was bling, and updated with modern components I was quite happy to explore mexico’s darkest off roads.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.climb.mx/assets/imgs/10247068594_d47b8a25c7_b.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.climb.mx/assets/imgs/10247068594_d47b8a25c7_b.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>